Mss.Rec.105 Mss.Rec.105
American Philosophical Society
Lummi recordings
1974
Mss.Rec.105
American Philosophical Society
20.0 Reel(s)
Linguistic field recordings, recorded in Whatcom County, Washington, June - August 1974, with consultant Al Charles. Includes stories relating to Lummi history, descriptions of social customs, descriptions of museum artifacts, descriptions of how to prepare various kinds of traditional foods, and elicited sentences. Majority of material given in Lummi and later reviewed and translated.
20 sound tape reels (21 hr., 29 min.): analog, 3 3/4 ips, 2 track, mono; 5 in.
Bowman, Elizabeth
Charles, Al
Demers, Richard A.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Presented by Richard Demers in 1976 (Acc. 1976 1750r). This material was recorded with the assistance of a Phillips Fund grant.
General note
The reels in the library's collection are copies of the collector's original reel-to-reels. The original tapes are numbered 22-41. The original tape 28, track 1 was copied to both tracks of the library's tape 28. The content of original tape 28, track 2 is not on the library's copy.
Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Fishing; Lummi Indians--Folklore; Lummi Indians--Food; Lummi Indians--History; Lummi Indians--Material culture; Lummi Indians--Social life and customs; North Straits Salish language; Northwest Coast Indians; Sound recordings
- Audio recordings
  - Names of Puget Sound area tribes, 1974-06-27; 22-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:31; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Scope and Contents note
    In Lummi only.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Puget Sound; Lummi dialect; North Straits Salish language; Puget Sound Salish Indians; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Story of Si'maelh, 1974-06-28; 22-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:16:47; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Story told in Lummi only, with introductory remarks in English.
    Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Folklore; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Brief discussion of a mask, 1974-06-28; 22-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:10; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Lummi dialect; Masks; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Going over the Story of Si'maelh [1 of 3], 1974-07-01; 22-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:34:35; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of a previously recorded story in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. The recording speed gradually increases over the course of this program. The played-back material on the recording is significantly distorted.
  - Going over the Story of Si'maelh [2 of 3], 1974-07-01; 22-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:41; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of a previously recorded story in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. The played-back material on the recording is significantly distorted.
  - Going over the Story of Si'maelh [3 of 3], 1974-07-02; 22-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:26:18; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Description of islands, 1974-07-03; 23-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:01; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Islands--Washington (State); Lummi dialect; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Snups lectures, 1974-07-03; 23-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:16; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Consultant's recollections in Lummi of advice he received from his parents, with introductory remarks in English.
    Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Social life and customs; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Going over snups lectures: relatives, marriage customs, and hospitality, 1974-07-03; 23-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:08; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. The played-back material on the recording is significantly distorted.
    Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Kinship; Lummi Indians--Marriage customs and rites; Lummi Indians--Social life and customs; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Discussion of the meaning of "snups", 1974-07-09; 23-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:44; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Lummi dialect; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Discussion of a stone used in fishing and miscellaneous grammar, 1974-07-09; 23-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:17; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Fishing; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Going over snups lectures: taking good care of old people, 1974-07-09; 23-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:24; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Social life and customs; North Straits Salish language; Older people--Care; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Going over snups lectures: social status, 1974-07-10; 24-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:30; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. Recording speed increases over the course of the program, with frequent fluctations.
  - Going over snups lectures: social status, 1974-07-10; 24-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:10; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. Recording speed increases over the course of the program, with frequent fluctations. The speed has been digitally adjusted at 13:38 through end of program.
  - Going over snups lectures: kinship and genealogy, 1974-07-10; 24-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:36; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. Recording speed increases over the course of the program, with frequent fluctations. The speed has been digitally adjusted through 5:27, and again at a higher rate from 5:27 through the end of the recording.
    Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Puget Sound; Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Kinship; Lummi Indians--Social life and customs; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Going over snups lectures: marriage customs, 1974-07-10; 24-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:47; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts.
  - Going over snups lectures: relatives and marriage customs, 1974-07-11; 24-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:26:08; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Going over snups lectures: marriage customs, 1974-07-11; 25-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:45; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. Recording speed increases over the course of the program, with some fluctations.
    Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Marriage customs and rites; Lummi Indians--Social life and customs; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Discussion of preserving blackberries, 1974-07-12; 25-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:33; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Recording contains uncorrected background hum.
    Blackberries; Food--Preservation; Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Food; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Going over snups lectures: how to greet people, 1974-07-12; 25-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:29:24; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. Recording speed increases over the course of the program, with frequent fluctations. Speed has been digitally readjusted in sections at different rates, from 00:00-13:05, 13:05-21:40, 21:40-25:08, 25:08-end. Recording contains partially corrected background hum.
    Hospitality; Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Social life and customs; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Sound check, counting from 1-10 in Lummi, 1974-07-12; 25-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:14; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Discussion of ways to prepare salmon and other foods for eating, 1974-07-16; 25-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:34; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Descriptions of food preparation and kinds of foods, each given in both Lummi and English. Recording speed increases over the course of the program, primarily near the end, with some fluctations. Recording contains partially corrected background hum.
    Food--Preservation; Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Food; North Straits Salish language; Pacific salmon; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Discussion on ways to prepare clams and blackberries, 1974-07-16; 26-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:08; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Recording contains partially corrected background hum.
    Blackberries; Clams; Lummi dialect; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - The story of sqoloxst (Lummi), 1974-07-17; 26-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:23:18; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Folklore; Lummi Indians--History; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Discussion of Lummi history, 1974-07-17; 26-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:56; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Baker, Mount (Wash.); Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--History; Nooksack Indians; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Discussion of differences in pronunciation among dialects, 1974-07-17; 26-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:13; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Bald eagle; English language--Pronunciation; Lummi dialect; North Straits Salish language--Pronunciation; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - The story of sqoloxst (English), 1974-07-17; 26-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:20:58; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Description of artifacts: arrow, 1974-07-18; 26-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:53; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Description of an arrow, given in Lummi only. Recording contains partially corrected background hum.
    Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Material culture; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Descriptions of artifacts: arrow, berry basket, duck arrow, halibut hook, jewelry, large basket, 1974-07-18; 27-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:40; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Recording speed increases over the course of the program, with frequent fluctations. The speed has been partially corrected through digital adjustment. The tape is misidentified on the recording as tape 26.
    Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Fishing; Lummi Indians--Material culture; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Lummi sentences, 1974-07-18; 27-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:49; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Recording speed increases over the course of the program, with frequent fluctations. The speed has been partially corrected through digital adjustment.
  - Discussion of ways to prepare crabs for eating, 1974-07-18; 27-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:47; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Crabs; Lummi dialect; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Lummi sentences, 1974-07-25; 27-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:04; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Program contains some print-through of audio on the opposite side of the tape.
  - Lummi sentences, 1974-07-25; 27-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:21:37; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Recording contains significant print-through of audio from the opposite side of the tape through 10:03.
  - Lummi sentences, 1974-07-26; 27-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:11:03; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Lummi sentences emphasizing negation, 1974-07-26; 28-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:20:23; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Going over snups material from 3 July 1974, 1974-07-26; 28-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:35; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Social life and customs; North Straits Salish language; Potlatch; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Lummi sentences involving embedding, 1974-07-30; 29-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:50; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Uncorrected line hum through 12:19.
  - Lummi sentences involving embedding, 1974-07-30; 29-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:50; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Story of the hunters and the stars, 1974-07-30; 29-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:54; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Hunters--Folklore; Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Folklore; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Going over descriptions of artifacts: small berry basket, scraper, 1974-07-31; 29-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:21:00; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. Description of scraper begins at 10:55.
  - Going over descriptions of artifacts: mortar & pestle, reef net, 1974-07-31; 30-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:33:17; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Lummi sentences, 1974-08-01; 30-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:21; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Going over descriptions of artifacts: reef net, 1974-08-01; 30-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:53; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Going over descriptions of artifacts: reef net, 1974-08-01; 31-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:24; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Going over descriptions of artifacts: rattle, 1974-08-01; 31-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:22:02; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. A 54-second gap silent gap starting at 7:45 on the original recording has been shortened to 3 seconds.
    Lummi dance; Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Material culture; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Lummi sentences, 1974-08-01; 31-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:36; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Going over descriptions of artifacts: items used in dancing, 1974-08-02; 31-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:34:04; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. Items described in recording include clubs, deer hooves, and various decorations. A 55-second gap silent gap starting at 21:50 on the original recording has been shortened to 3 seconds.
  - Going over descriptions of artifacts: arrowhead/spearhead, 1974-08-05; 32-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:15; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. A 40-second gap silent gap starting at 12:48 on the original recording has been shortened to 3 seconds.
    Arrowheads; Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Material culture; Lummi Indians--Social life and customs; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Going over descriptions of artifacts: arrowhead/spearhead, 1974-08-05; 32-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:14; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. A 40-second gap silent gap starting at 19:51 on the original recording has been shortened to 3 seconds.
  - Going over descriptions of artifacts: arrowhead/spearhead, 1974-08-06; 33-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:16:01; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Going over descriptions of artifacts: adze, 1974-08-06; 33-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:00; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Adzes; Canoes and canoeing--Design and construction; Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Material culture; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Going over descriptions of artifacts: model war canoe, 1974-08-06; 33-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:20; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Canoes and canoeing; Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Material culture; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Going over descriptions of artifacts: model war canoe, with discussion of slave raids, 1974-08-06; 33-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:39; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. Primarily concerns discussion of raids in the past by groups from the north looking for people to make into slaves. The left channel has been digitally duplicated to the right channel due to a severe print-through effect on original tape's right channel. Contains a faint echo distortion throughout.
    Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--History; Lummi Indians--Material culture; North Straits Salish language; Slavery; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Going over descriptions of artifacts: model war canoe, with discussion of slave raids, 1974-08-07; 33-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:24; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. Primarily concerns discussion of raids in the past by groups from the north looking for people to make into slaves. The left channel has been digitally duplicated to the right channel due to a severe print-through effect on original tape's right channel.
  - Going over descriptions of artifacts: model war canoe, discussion of slave raids, spindle, 1974-08-07; 34-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:03; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. Primarily concerns discussion of raids in the past by groups from the north looking for people to make into slaves. Also includes elicited sentences.
  - Going over descriptions of artifacts: items used in canoeing, 1974-08-08; 34-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:18; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Going over description of preparing a meal, 1974-08-08; 34-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:44; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. This program has a faint print-through of audio on the reverse side of the tape.
    Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Food; Lummi Indians--Social life and customs; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - Going over description of preparing a meal, 1974-08-08; 35-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:25:25; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Lummi sentences of the type "Who does the boy know?", 1974-08-09; 35-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:40; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Lummi sentences of the type "Who does the boy know?", 1974-08-09; 35-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:05; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Going over description of preparing a meal, 1974-08-15; 36-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:04; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Going over description of preparing a meal, 1974-08-15; 36-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:52; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Going over description of preparing a meal, 1974-08-16; 36-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:26:14; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Going over description of preparing a meal, 1974-08-16; 37-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:52; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Going over description of preparing a meal, 1974-08-19; 37-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:07; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Going over description of preparing a meal, 1974-08-19; 37-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:00; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Going over description of a meal, 1974-08-19; 38-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:37; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - The stommish story, 1974-08-19; 38-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:05; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--History; North Straits Salish language; Slavery; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - The stommish story, 1974-08-20; 38-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:22:23; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - The stommish story, 1974-08-20; 38-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:59; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Discussion of how the Lummis drove away the raiders of the north for the last time, 1974-08-21; 39-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:44; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - How to roast a duck, 1974-08-21; 39-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:16:15; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Cookery (Duck); Lummi dialect; Lummi Indians--Food; North Straits Salish language; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - How to roast a duck, 1974-08-21; 39-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:40; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. Audio contains intermittent scratches.
  - How to roast a duck, 1974-08-22; 39-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:19; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - How to roast a duck, 1974-08-22; 40-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:38; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
  - Anecdote about seeing a Bigfoot footprint, 1974-08-23; 40-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:48; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Predominantly in English.
    Lummi dialect; North Straits Salish language; Sasquatch; Whatcom County (Wash.)
  - How to roast a duck, 1974-08-23; 40-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:26:49; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. First 5:00 an anecdote about a bigfoot sighting from decades earlier. Audio contains partially corrected background hum.
  - How to roast a duck, 1974-08-23; 41-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:19:38; Bowman, Elizabeth; Charles, Al; Demers, Richard A.
    Translation and transcription of previously recorded material in Lummi as it is played back to the consultant in short excerpts. Audio contains partially corrected background hum.